<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse by R. Lewes, Baccheler of Divinitie, concerning Isaac his testament, disposed by the Lord to Iacobs comfort, though it were intednded to Esau by his father; shewing, that the counsel of God shal stand, albeit the whole worlde withstande it.</title>
            <author>Lewes, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119665</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20327</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05404)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20327)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 474:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse by R. Lewes, Baccheler of Divinitie, concerning Isaac his testament, disposed by the Lord to Iacobs comfort, though it were intednded to Esau by his father; shewing, that the counsel of God shal stand, albeit the whole worlde withstande it.</title>
                  <author>Lewes, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, printer to that famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D. XCIIII. [1594]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Isaac his testament.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED <hi>AT PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LES</hi> Croſſe, by R. LEWES, Bacche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Divinitie, concerning <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Teſtament, diſpoſed by the Lord to <hi>Iacobs</hi> comfort, though it were intended to <hi>Eſau</hi> by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſhewing, that the counſel of God ſhal ſtand, albeit the whole worlde withſtande it.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>AC: OX</head>
               <figDesc>coat of arms or blazon</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by IOSEPH BARNES, <hi>Printer to that famous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> M.D.XCIIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL AND MOST <hi>WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIE KNIGHT, HENRY VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON,</hi> his moſt loving and munificent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, Grace, mercy, and peace in Chriſt bee multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is no ende of making many bookes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and much reading is a wearineſſe to the fleſh: and in our careleſſe daies, bookes may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeme to want rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, then readers to want bookes: whether men deſire to taſt, and ſee howe gratious the Lorde is, in learned and Godly diſcourſes;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.</note> or otherwiſe feede their own fancies on the chaffe and huskes of vnlearned and vnſavory pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets; fitter for children, then men, for infidels then Chriſtians, for ſwine, then for the prodigal ſonne. This conſideration well digeſted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.</note> had wel nigh induced mee to reſolve with Licimus, that neither learned, nor vnlearned ſhoulde reade any of my doinges: not the one, becauſe they are of that ſtupiditie, that they conceive not ones meaning; not the other, as beeing ſo wiſe, that I may diſpare of ſatisfiyng their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
<pb facs="tcp:20327:3"/>
iudgementes. And doubtleſſe, had not my good friend Maſter <hi>Wright,</hi> your Worſhips moſt diligent and learned Preacher, (at what time you moſt honourably managed your worthy embaſſage in <hi>Fraunce</hi> of late) had not that paineful member of the Church, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, in peace and warre, devoted to <hi>Mars,</hi> as well as to <hi>Mercury</hi> when need required, &amp; Gods glory craved his ſervice, had not that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſouldier of Chriſt in the vniverſity, citie, and country, yea and in the field among the pikes, having pervſed this ſermon, greatly animated mee to publiſh it: I woulde never have brought ſtickes into the woode, and caſt water into the ſea, as I doe. Another ſpeciall motive that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered my determination, was this, that I might ſome way teſtifie my moſt gratefull minde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, &amp; my very ſingular good <hi>Lady,</hi> for your ſundry, rare, &amp; vndeſerved favours, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped &amp; multiplied vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. If any of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have iuſt cauſe, both to love, and honour their loving and liberal benefactors &amp; patrons: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may that learned Preacher Maſter <hi>Iennings,</hi> that grave Devine, Maſter <hi>Sheward,</hi> that zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Trumpettor of Gods word, Maſter <hi>Wright,</hi> with others of good note in that famous vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie, but chiefly I, acknowledge your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as a true patterne of all patrons. All men ſee your magnanimity, prudence, temperance,
<pb facs="tcp:20327:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
affability, conſtancy, and zeale to Gods glorie: but wee feede daily on your vertue, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie God for ſuch a ſtay at home, and ſuch an ornament abroad, as is a ſpectacle of iuſtice, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, and true Godlines. The Lorde alwaies bleſſe you with all his bleſſings, and bleſſe vs with you, to the vnſpeakeable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of Gods Church, for whoſe good, he hath raiſed you vp.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips moſt bounden, <hi>R. LEWES.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>This xviij of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 27. verſe. 1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And when <hi>Iſaac</hi> was old, and his eies dimme (ſo that hee coulde not ſee) he called <hi>Eſau</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, and ſaid vnto him, my ſon; and he anſwered him, I am heere. Then he ſaide, beholde I am now olde and knowe not the day of my death. Wherefore nowe I pray thee, take thine inſtruments, thy quiver and thy bow, &amp; get thee to the field, that thou maiſt take me ſome veniſon. Then make me ſavory meate ſuch as I love, and bring it to me that I may eat, and that I may bleſſe thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I die. Now <hi>Rebecca</hi> hearde when <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſpake to <hi>Eſau</hi> his ſonne: and <hi>Eſau</hi> went into the fielde to hunte for veniſon and to bring it. Then <hi>Rebecca</hi> ſpake vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> her ſonne, ſaying, behold I have heard thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther talking with <hi>Eſau</hi> thy, &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Eſau</hi> for a portion of meate, had moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely &amp; ſecurely ſolde his birthright: as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>verſe.</hi> 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. and when he had ſo degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of kinde, that hee made a covenant even by marriage with the inhabitantes of <hi>Canaan,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God had accurſed; when he thus forſooke the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis of ſalvation, and made no more reckoning of his birthright, then if it had not beene woorth a
<pb facs="tcp:20327:5"/>
ſtrawe: Beholde (Right Honourable, worſhipful, and in our Lord beloved) old <hi>Iſaac</hi> his father not onely beareth with all this, but ſo doteth on <hi>Eſau</hi> his deere ſon, that being blind in his eies, but farre more blinde in his affection, he both loveth &amp; eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Eſau,</hi> yea he preferreth him before <hi>Iacob,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choſen of God. It was overmuch lenity in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> to tolerate the enormities of <hi>Eſau,</hi> to ſuffer him to take two wives, yea to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites:</hi> but as in theſe points to bewray his infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſo to promiſe <hi>Eſau</hi> that bleſſing, which God had promiſed to <hi>Iacob,</hi> it ſavoureth marveilouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the corruption of fleſh and bloud. Yet for all his weakenes, very rare and notable was the faith of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who beeing a poore waifaring man, when he received that promiſe from God, thou ſhalt bee Lord and heire of this country, when notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hee had not ſo much as water to drinke; yet in deſpite of <hi>Satan,</hi> and mauger the world, he remaineth ſtedfaſt in this, that God will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him: and albeit his houſe of clay, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is duſt, doe fall and moulder in the earth; yet the truth of God ſhall continue and have his full power and vertue. Thus leaving his ſence and living by faith, he addreſſeth himſelfe to make his laſt will and teſtament: wherein his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of faith, is ſomewhat obſcured by the dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his affection, which he followeth ſo farre, that he fighteth againſt God, overthwarteth his
<pb facs="tcp:20327:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
decree, and wrongeth his ſonne <hi>Iacob,</hi> though hee never thinke of it. In this teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1. the cauſe, 2. the eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: the cauſe is either out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or inward: the outward is efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or finall: the efficient is either principal, or ſubordinat: the efficient principall cauſe is God: the efficient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate cauſe is <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who is aboute to ſet his houſe in order before hee die: the finall cauſe is, that there might ariſe no controverſie betweene his ſonnes after his departure: the inwarde is either material or formall material, an heire to be ordained: the forme ſtandeth in the inſtitution of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſubſtitution of <hi>Eſau:</hi> In the inſtitution of <hi>Iacob,</hi> wee ſee who is bleſſed, and by what meanes: the party that is bleſſed is <hi>Iacob,</hi> the means are the perſuaſive pollicie of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and <hi>Iacobs</hi> bold adventure. The perſwaſions and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>Rebecca</hi> are <hi>A Tuto,</hi> ver. 13. thou maiſt ſafelie doe it, on me be the curſe. <hi>A facili,</hi> it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie done: by putting on <hi>Eſaus</hi> garmentes, verſe the tenth, fifteenth, and ſixteenth <hi>Abvtili,</hi> thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will bleſſe thee before hee die: not with an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, but with a moſt ſingular bleſſing. By <hi>Iacobs</hi> bolde adventure in putting his mothers counſell in execution: in affirming himſelfe to bee <hi>Eſau,</hi> the eldeſt and deareſt ſonne: in preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the providence of God, working for him: in offering his father meate, and drinke: as alſo by <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> his errour in iudging rather by his hands the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:20327:6"/>
by his eares: In the ſubſtitution of <hi>Eſau,</hi> the ſpirit of God ſheweth the perſon that is bleſſed with a ſecondary bleſſing, and the perſon that bleſſeth. In <hi>Eſau</hi> who is now bleſſed with a kinde of bleſſing, firſt wee ſee his importunity to have a bleſsing, which appeareth in wordes and weeping, ſecondly his hatred againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi> becauſe of the bleſſing. <hi>Iſaac</hi> being aſtonied beyonde meaſure, firſt confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the bleſſing to <hi>Iacob,</hi> perceiving nowe at length, that it was Gods determination, and that any man could not, a good man ſhoulde not hinder it; he laboureth not wilfully to alter it, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly yeeldeth to Gods pleaſure, though it were at firſt contrarie to his will. Secondlie hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcome with <hi>Eſaus</hi> teares, pronounceth on earthly and corporall bleſſing, to that carnall and vngodly man. In the event wee ſee the exile of <hi>Iacob:</hi> he hath not the principall bleſſing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſpeciall croſſe. Secondly the motives which his mother vſed, that hee ſhoulde departe: firſt, by ſhewing him his daunger: ſecondelie, the meanes howe to avoide it. In the looking glaſſe of this hiſtorie, I ſee two notable images repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to our view: the firſt is the frailty of man, the ſeconde is the faith of Gods children; beſides many other advertiſementes, both pleaſant and profitable, which I will pointe at by the waye. The frailtie of man is ſet downe in the purpoſe of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and in the practiſe of <hi>Rebecca.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:20327:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
frailtie of <hi>Iſaac</hi> is mentioned in the foure firſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: the infirmity of <hi>Rebecca</hi> in the diſcourſe of the fact, till the 29. verſe. The faith of <hi>Iſaac, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> is manifeſt throughout the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie: albeit, it be ſomewhat darkened with the blinde affection of the one, and the indirect meanes of the other. Thus oftentimes by the interpoſition of the earth, and carnall thinges, the ſonne of righteouſneſſe is eclipſed in the moſt deere Saintes and ſervauntes of GOD. In this hiſtorie wee learne the indubitable truth of GODS promiſes: and the continuall care hee hath of his Saintes: and that hee ſo fulfilleth his woorde, that it commeth to paſſe beyonde mans expectation. <hi>Iacob</hi> is never ſo neere his fathers bleſsing, as when hee ſeemeth to be out of hope of a bleſsing, and in feare of a curſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Eſau</hi> was never ſo ſure of the bleſſing, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day that he loſt it. <hi>Iacob</hi> was never ſo doubtful as that day hee had the bleſsing, nor <hi>Eſau</hi> ever ſo certaine (in his opinion) as that houre that hee loſt it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 21 30.</note> No humane counſel canne alter the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell or interrupt the covenaunt of GOD. They which the Lorde will advaunce, ſhall be advaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. The Lord ſuffereth the iuſt other whiles to fal, to'erre, to be deceived; partly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may know their own weakenes, &amp; partly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may have the more compaſſion on others. Moreover the Lorde revealeth that ſometimes to the leſſer, which hee
<pb facs="tcp:20327:7"/>
doth not to the greater, as to <hi>Rebecca</hi> &amp; not to <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac. Iſaac</hi> perceiving the favour of God to bee the beſt inheritance that his ſon can have, is careful to bleſſe him before he die. This good man is pure &amp; cleane, yet not ſo, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he hath neede, that his feete (I meane his affections) be waſhed. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. That holy Matron <hi>Rebecca,</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promis which was made 40 years before: we ſcarce reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the promiſes of God (which he made lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince) but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated yeſterday vnto vs. <hi>Rebecca</hi> inſtructed her ſon above all thinges to ſeeke that excellent bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: we inſtruct ours how they maie live here, but not how they may live for ever. <hi>Rebecca</hi> woulde not have <hi>Iacob</hi> in anie wiſe to marrie with the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> we beſtow our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on popiſh <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> and are mingled with them. <hi>Rebecca</hi> knew that her husbande erred: yet ſhe doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult over him, ſhee doth not withſtande him, ſhee is officious towardes him: but among vs, if any man erre never ſo little, yee ſhall have them that wil tel it at <hi>Gath,</hi> and proclaime it in the ſtreetes of <hi>Askalon:</hi> that the daughters of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> may reioice, and that the children of the vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed may triumph. We may ſee in this hiſtorie, that <hi>Iacob</hi> feareth to lie, though it be for his own, and to obtaine a notable bleſſing hee ſtaieth, hee ſtaggereth, he doubteth: but there are many that ſay they are <hi>Iacobs,</hi> who make no bones of lying, of deceit, and faining: never fearing a curſe, as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20327:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
did, though they ſeeke other mens right, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> his owne. In <hi>Eſau</hi> wee have an expreſſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of worldlinges, and Atheiſtes: firſt in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency of body, in taking two wives: ſecondly in his profannes of minde, in matching with <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites:</hi> thirdly in that hee grieveth his parents with his vndutifulnes: fourthly in that hee was a hunter, it agreed well with his quality, who hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for worldly things: fiftly in that hee tarried ſo long, that he loſt the bleſſing: he came but a minut to late; but yet two late: the worldelings doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to late: the fooliſh Virgins come when the bride-grome is entred: the rich man in hel would faine have one drop of mercy, who delaied to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it, while it was ſo ful and freely offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him vppon the earth. <hi>Eſaus</hi> will hunte ſo long for the honoures, pleaſures, and wealth of this worlde: that they will come ſhorte of the bleſſing of GOD. <hi>Eſau</hi> weepeth for an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde bleſsing, not caring for the inwarde and ſpirituall bleſsinges of GOD: ſo the worlde: lings if they faile of theſe outwarde tranſitorie bleſsings, then doe they houle and crie out with <hi>Eſau: hinc illae lachrimae:</hi> the loſſe of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, the loſſe of GODS favour, the loſſe of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vnity, the loſſe of many ſpirituall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall bleſſings will not ſo much grieve the <hi>Eſaus</hi> of this worlde, as to be deprived of one car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bleſsing. Now that yee ſee the ſumme of
<pb facs="tcp:20327:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the hiſtory, before I come to the frailty of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> I cannot but commende vnto you a lively image of his faith, in this his laſt will and teſtament. This diſpoſing of his earthly thinges, and this pronouncing of the bleſsing of God to his ſonne after him, was a voluntary reſigning vppe, and giving over of all worldly goods, with a reſolute preparation of his minde to die, and to bid this troubleſome life adiew: reſting himſelfe wholy, &amp; ſolely reioicing in a holy &amp; a heavenly hope of an eternal manſion, which God had provided for his choſen <hi>Abraham</hi> his father before he died, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie his faith to God, and to prevent all occaſion of ſtrife betweene his children, bequeathed to the reſt ſundry giftes: but the inheritaunce hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>highted <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> before his death gave evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent teſtimony of his faith to God, and love to his Church, when he tooke order touching the place of his buriall: when hee exhorted his children to concord and vnity: when hee prophecied ſo plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> comming, and bleſt all his ſonnes with ſingular bleſſings. He ſhewed, that when his body was in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> his hearte was in <hi>Canaan</hi> the promiſed land. Semblably <hi>Ioſeph</hi> following <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 48</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſteps, did ſet things in order before he died: and tooke an oath of the ſons of <hi>Iſrael</hi> his brethren, to cary his bones out of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> building vpon the promiſe of God, which he repeateth at his death, that God will doubtles vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb facs="tcp:20327:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them, &amp; bring them out of that land, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which he promiſed <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> &amp; <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> endeth his life, <hi>cignea cantione,</hi> or rather <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deute</hi> 31.</note> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſweet ſong and a heavenly ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; appointeth <hi>Ioſua</hi> to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in his place. <hi>David</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king drawing neer vnto his death, charged <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſaying, Take heede to the charge of the Lord thy God, to walke in his waies, &amp; keepe his ſtatuts, &amp; his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; his teſtimonies, as it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.</note> that thou maiſt proſper in al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doeſt, &amp; in every thing wherevnto thou turneſt thee &amp;c. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he appointeth <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſucceed him. When the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death is denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>Eſay</hi> vnto <hi>Ezechia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.</note> hee is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded in the name of the Lord, to ſet his houſe in order before he die. This practiſe of holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſerved aſwel to ſhew their faith, as to cut off occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſtrife, which els might enſue. And thus the Saints of God doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their faith,<note place="margin">☉</note> &amp; the proofe of their love, aſwel in death as in life: whereas the wicked as they live without love, ſo they dy without faith, as they live without fear, ſo they die without hope, as they have bodies without life, ſo have they ſouls without God. And among that rabble, even blinde <hi>Baalam</hi> himſelfe, who ſaw leſſe then his Aſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.10.</note> and knew nothing of the law, yet will not faile to ſaie, I wiſh my ſoule to die the death of the righteous, and my ende to be ſuch as theirs ſhalbe. I deſire to
<pb facs="tcp:20327:9"/>
be ioined with the race of faithfull <hi>Abraham:</hi> but who cauſeth the wicked ſometimes to have theſe affections, and to vtter ſuch ſpeeches? who, but the Lord, who ſetteth them vpon the earth, and wreſteth out this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them? Why <hi>Balaam,</hi> thou haſt let out thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to hier vnto wickednes, &amp; haſt ſet thy ſoule to ſale vnto covetouſnes, and art poſſeſſed with <hi>Satan,</hi> &amp; ſaiſt thou thus of the death of the righteous? what ſhal the faithful themſelves ſay, who know by experience, the moſt happy &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable truth of thy ſaying, who as they live in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, ſo they depart in that hope &amp; aſſurance? The wicked have a glauncing glimpes, a ſodden light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tany motion, even a ſmall taſt of the things that are heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly &amp; eternal: but in the hearts of the Godly, they are ſealed with Gods ſpirit, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his promiſes, &amp; write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a pen of yro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the print of a diamond, yea ingraven in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their ſouls. As for the teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked who as coales do kindle heat, and wood the fire, ſo have they kindled their natural corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; foſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the flame of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. How ſhould they te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their faith, ſeeing they have none? or tende to quietneſſe &amp; vnity, ſeeing they never ſought it? yea though their ſtolne waters may be ſweete, &amp; their bread pleaſant for a time:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.17.</note> yet the curſe of the Lord is in their houſes: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is bleſſed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prover.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 33.</note> Before thou make (reſting on Gods promiſes) thy laſte will and teſtament with
<pb facs="tcp:20327:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſee thou firſt make (obeying Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement) due reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with <hi>Zacheus:</hi> if thou have defrauded any man by forged cavillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by byting vſury, or by bloudy cruelty and oppreſsion, it is good to make a teſtament, but it is better to make reſtitution: neither is thy teſtament good without reſtitution. When thou leaveſt the worlde, wilt thou not leave wickednes, but at thy laſt gaſpe deale ſo vniuſtly, and conclude thy life with ſuch vnrighteous dealing, as to enrich thy children with the goods of other men? Doeſt thou ſo take thy farewell of the worlde, as if thou fearedſt not the iudgement of God, no not when thy ſoule is preſently ſummoned to his tribunall ſeat? Doeſt thou thinke that thou ſhalt not give an account of thy ſtewardſhip? O vniuſt ſervante, art thou ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched by <hi>Satan,</hi> that thou ſaieſt in thy hart, tuſh God doth not ſee it, the Lord doth not regarde it? Wil not the Lord take the matter into his hands, ſeeing the poore committeth himſelfe vnto the Lord, as to the helpe of the fatherleſſe? Wil not the Lord hear the deſire of the poore, ſeing he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared their harts? wil he not be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his ear vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Thinkeſt thou that the vnrighteous Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moniſtes ſhal inherite the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The hope of the vngodly is like the duſt that is blown away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the winde, &amp; like a thin fome that is ſcattered abroade with the ſtorme, &amp; as the ſmoke in the aire, and as the remembraunce of him paſſeth that carrieth
<pb facs="tcp:20327:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but for a day. Touching the neceſsity of a teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: if the Philoſopher denieth him to be a good man who in a civill ſedition is a neuter; how can hee bee a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od man, that ſeeing diſſention will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in his familie after his death, yet will not by opening his minde, and teſtifying his wil, cut off the cordes of domeſticall variaunce and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and procure the pleaſaunt harmonie of concorde to continue amonge his children? The matter of a teſtament is the diſpoſing of thinges which are poſſeſſed, either to the benefitte of the Church; (but theſe teſtamentes are deade, with the teſtators in olde time, and I woulde the Church might have her owne) or to the vſe of the poore; or to the behoofe of our friendes; or to the commoditie of our children. Both our heires and goodes are to bee conſidered: if our children bee our heires, nature alloweth it: if our friendes, thankefulneſſe accepteth it: if the poore, charitie commendeth it: if the Church or ſcholes of learning, religion approveth it. The goodes that are lawfully gotten, may liberallie be beſtowed on theſe good endes, and as they are called goodes, ſo I would to God the rich would doe ſome good with them: but that which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully taken by vſurie or extortion, ought ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilye to bee reſtored after Gods will in his teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not otherwiſe diſpoſed according to mans will in his teſtamente. Is the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:20327:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
teſtament of God, which commaundeth reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, both violated in his life by vniuſt exaction, and gaineſaide at his death by an iniurious teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The partridge gathereth an hoorde of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther birdes egges, ſitteth vpon them, and hatcheth them, but when they are fluſh, they flie away from her, for they know that of right they belong not to the partridge: ſemblably the vnrighteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon gleaneth in other mens fields, and reapeth the harveſt of poore men, but in ſhorte time they will flie away (for riches haue wings) or they wil ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him in little ſteede, yea they ſhall rather make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, then for him. Now that I may come to the frailty of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> having firſt concluded by the teſtaments of men, which are ordained to end ſtrife among the ſonnes of men, that the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God is appointed to end all contention in the family of God (albeit our adverſaries the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of light and dependers of darkenes, bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diffidence of the cauſe, &amp; the hard opinion they conceiue of the ſcriptures, doe affirme and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch the contrary) Wee ſay with <hi>Optatus</hi> an auncient learned and godly father, that we know that Chriſt hath dealt with vs, as an earthly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is woont with his children: who fearing leſt they ſhould fal out after his deceaſe, ſets down his wil in writing vnder witneſſes, &amp; if there ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny debate amonge the brethren, they goe to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: he whoſe worde muſt ende our contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie
<pb facs="tcp:20327:11"/>
is <hi>Chriſt:</hi> let his will be ſought in his teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: we are brethren, why doe we ſtrive? Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther died not vnteſtate: hee made a teſtament and ſo died. Men do ſtrive about the goods of the dead till the teſtament be brought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they yeeld to have it opened &amp; read: the iudge doth harken: the counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are ſilent: the crier biddeth peace: the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are attentive, that the wordes of the dead may be read and heard. He lieth voide of ſence and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his grave, and his wordes prevaile; <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſitteth in heaven, and is his word gainſaide? Open it, let vs read it, we are brethren, why doe we ſtrive? Let our mindes be pacified, our father hath not left vs without a teſtament: he that made the teſtament is living for ever. Hee doth heare our wordes: he knoweth his owne words: let vs read, why doe we ſtrive? Yea wee ſay with that choſen veſſell Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that the teſtament of God is not only profitable, but ſufficient and perfect: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as if <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe beeing an excellent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, yea if an Angell from heaven ſhould preach any point of faith or rule of life, I ſay not, againſt, but beſide the ſcripture, let him be accurſed. The divines of <hi>Lovain</hi> do cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d beſides the Scriptures (to be ment) againſt the ſcriptures; if theſe men were Doctors of the <hi>Arches</hi> we ſhould have profounde lawe: for ſo a cooſening fellowe might claime 1000. <hi>po,</hi> of a dead mans goods who had bequethed him a legacy of 20. <hi>ſh.</hi> &amp; the iudges
<pb facs="tcp:20327:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
might adiudge at him with ſafe conſciences, as not againſt the teſtament, albeit beſides the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: nay they might doe this vniuſtice to man w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> far better reaſon, then the Papiſts doe that diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to God, by howe much the teſtament of God is far more abſolute then mans, and more ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to finiſh al controverſies, &amp; more perfect to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect in faith and obedience. Our duty in <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> is faith working by love: faith embraceth ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doctrine: love requireth a godly life: ſoundnes of doctrine is held, if truth be taught and falſhod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed: godlines of life is kept, if a man fly from evil and follow good. The holy ſcripture teacheth the truth, improveth errour, correcteth iniquitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth to righteouſneſſe, and ſo containeth the whole duety of man: yea even of the man of God, in whom greater perfection is required. But this wil not they ſee, who being blinded with affection and banded into faction, doe labour to diſhonour Gods word, and to bewitch mens ſoules: ſeducing the ambitious w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> promiſes of honour, the ſimple &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of learning; who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceive their hypocriſie to be piety, their ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, their falſhood to be faithfulnes, their traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, their indulgences to be <hi>Chriſts</hi> pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, their holy father to be <hi>Chriſts</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. But to returne to <hi>Iſaac</hi> &amp; his infir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mity. The ſpirit of God ſheweth, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was old, &amp; his eies began to be dimme, he could not ſee,
<pb facs="tcp:20327:12"/>
he was fully reſolved and determined to bleſſe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> his ſonne, whom he ſhould have had in dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, becauſe he enſtranged himſelfe from God, and as much as lay in him, made the promiſe of ſalvation of no effect. For what might have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Church of God, if the ſtocke of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had ioined with the <hi>Canaanites? Iſaac</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought more to have beene touched, ſeeing his ſonne to bee ſo prophane: he not only offendeth in not vſing fatherly ſeverity and correction, but he ſo doteth on <hi>Eſau,</hi> that by his will this prophane monſter ſhould enioy the bleſſing of God. He was no doubt the miniſter of God, and a ſingular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and led an Angels life among men: and yet nowe beeing ledde by his blinde affection, having the charge to bleſſe the choſen of God, he dealeth, as if himſelfe were appointer and author of the bleſſing. God had done him that honour to make him his miniſter in bleſſing, as to ſay I wil bleſſe whom I thinke good, but the teſtimony ſhal come out of thy mouth, thou ſhalt be my meſſenger, I commit this to thy credit &amp; charge, as to the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and keeper of my promiſe: that which thou pronounceſt ſhalbe autentike: and I will ratifie it in heaven. God had done him this honour, and yet hee ſuffereth himſelfe to bee ſo ſnared in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſeduced by affection, that hee ſwarveth quite contrary from that which his office requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and here the Lord wil teach vs that his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb facs="tcp:20327:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
againſt mans purpoſe ſhal have his effect. The Prieſtes in the lawe did not only offer, pray, and teach, but they bleſſed the people as figures of Chriſt. The Lord communicateth his benefites and bleſſings vnto vs by the handes of his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Blaſphemous are the Papiſts, who affirme that a mortal man may diſpoſe of Gods bleſſings and graces at his pleaſure. And curſed are the Anabaptiſts, who refuſe the miniſtery of men and will be taught immediatly of God, moſt fondly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing inferiour meanes, and with wings moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting above the cloudes: is not God ſufficient (ſay the Anabaptiſts) to inſtruct vs? Is the holy ghoſt in the handes of men to beſtow? What neede all this preaching? To what ende ſerveth ſo much reading? Canne not God inſpiring vs, touch our harts without having our eares ſo battered with the tongues of preachers? but doe not theſe fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall ſpirites know, that God will vſe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of men, and yet not be tyed to them? Doe they not know, that God hath ordained that faith ſhall come by hearing? Knowe they not, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath given ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, ſome Evangeliſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> ſome Paſtores and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, for the gathering togither of the Saintes, for the worke of the miniſtery, and for the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body of Chriſt? how long to endure? till we al meete togither in the vnity of faith, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſonne of God into a perfect man. And
<pb facs="tcp:20327:13"/>
vnto the meaſure of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> age of the fulneſſe of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> As touching <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who was Gods miniſter to bleſſe, we ſee how hee is intangled with an inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affection. And here let vs meditate &amp; ponder, how often, how ſodenly, how forcibly our blind af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections doe ruſh vppon vs, mooving vs to bite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and oppoſe our ſelves againſt his wil. As a <hi>Bull</hi> being chafed puſheth with his hornes; ſo our vnbrideled deſires and vnruly affections doe drive and raviſh vs in ſuch wiſe, that like mightie <hi>Nimrods</hi> in the quarrell of the fleſh, wee dare wage battell againſt the plaine woorde and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. Theſe affections of ours as the waves and windes, the ſtormes and quickeſandes of our ſoules, do ſo toſſe and tormoile vs vp and downe, that even the beſt Pilottes are faine to ſtrike ſaile, and reaſon it ſelfe is driven ſometimes to forſake the helme. I maie reſemble our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>Eli</hi> his children: whom the father ſo coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kred and forbare, that the Lorde tolde him that hee honoured them more then God; ſo deale wee with our affections: wee beare with them, wee yeelde vnto them, we are ruled by them, wee dote vpon them. As <hi>Eli</hi> demaunded of his ſonnes, why they did ſuch and ſuch things, &amp; ſaid doe ſo no more my ſons, it is no good reporte that I heare of you, for you make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords people to preſume againſt him by tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſions; but more then ſpeake rough
<pb facs="tcp:20327:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he did not, but let them have the ful forth in ſinne, as if he had chid them with his tongue, and ſtriked them faire and ſoftly on the head with his hand; ſo we aſke our affections ſometimes, why they are ſo vnruly againſt reaſon, ſo outragious againſt gods ſpirit, ſo offenſive to the children of God, we bidde them ceaſe, but we never bridle them, we never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them, we never hate and abhorre them, we let them have their force, ſtil we are ſoone pleaſed with them, and in ſo doing we preferre the fruites of our fleſh, before the fruites of the ſpirit of God. Well, <hi>Eli</hi> did ſo long cocker his children, that they cauſed him to breake his necke: yea the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and affections that are nouriſhed in vs and cheriſhed of vs, may be ſo long ſuffered, and theſe weeds may be ſo watered, that they may bring vs to a worſe ende then <hi>Eli.</hi> A man beeing ledde with his affection doth ſeeme to deale with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as perfumers deale with oiles, who never ceaſe medling and mingling of them till there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine no ſent of oile at al: ſo the reaſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo medled and mingled with his vaine deſires and delightes, that there remaineth almoſt no ſavour of the ſpirite at all. <hi>Plutarch</hi> marveiled that the feete of our bodies ſhoulde bee ſo readye to goe or to ſtaye, when our minde looſeth or pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth backe the bridle: and that on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie parte our affections beeing the feete of our
<pb facs="tcp:20327:14"/>
ſoules ſhould carry vs away headlong for any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint that we can make. Whereas imagination ought to rule our ſenſes, and reaſon to rule our i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination, and religion to rule our reaſon: now the outward ſence carrieth away the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the imagination leadeth away reaſon: reaſon checketh religion, &amp; apperite overruleth our will. Our gratious God hath appointed the ſoule of man three principal partes in mans body: expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the three <hi>Ideas</hi> &amp; formes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealthes in one man: he hath appointed the king himſelfe, to wit, mans reaſon, to be in the head as in a prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pallace or caſtle, where the ſenſes as domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſervantes, ſhould continually attend on reaſon the king, as vpon the only ruler and directer. The ſecond part of the minde, to wit, the quicke &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive facultie of doing and diſpatching al thinges, cleaving to the breſt, and not farre from the head, to wit, the facultie of anger and the ſeate of affections, hath the Lord ioined with the Prince. The third which may be called the vnruly multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, being given to carnal pleaſures and corrupt deſires, is placed vnder the heart ſtringes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other two. The governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of reaſon is a <hi>Monarchia:</hi> the rule of the ordered affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons repreſenteth <hi>Ariſtocratia:</hi> the adminiſtration of the loweſt parte is <hi>Democratia.</hi> As reaſon without affections which are his handes (as it were) is weake and feeble: ſo the affections with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:20327:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reaſon are blinde, ſottiſh, and effeminate. The inferiour parts being given to delightes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, are ſo much the more addicted to contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: from whence are warres and contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you (ſaith <hi>Iames</hi>) are they not hence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſ.</hi> 1.</note> even of your luſtes that fight in your members? If reaſon and not luſt might beare rule, the contentions in law would ſoone be ended. But mainetaine luſt which is the cauſe, and contention which is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect muſt neede enſue. The ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mples and formes of common-wealthes are plainely repreſented vnto vs in families and houſholdes, which are as it were ſmall common-weales. The power which a father hath over his children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantes, doth ſhadow the princely power. The rule of the wife over her children and ſervantes, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the authoritie of Councellers, and Noble men, who are aſſociated to the Prince. That ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of the brethren or ſervantes, is an image of the multitude. The Philoſophers haue pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced mans life to bee of three ſortes: the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in action, the ſecond in contemplation, the thirde in pleaſures. This laſt which is ledde in pleaſures, is fitteſt for the baſeſt ſorte, as beeing a mere ſlavery, and a beaſtly bondage to carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes: the firſt which is occupied in action, if it want the feare of God, is heatheniſh, and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: the ſecond conſiſting in contemplation (if it want action) is idle and vnfruitful. If the ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:20327:15"/>
bee obedient to his father, the ſubiect to his Prince, affection to reaſon; if they keepe each one their proper place &amp; office without vſurping: then is the regiment Monaſticall of the ſoule in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and Oeconomicall of the father over his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Politicall of a Prince over his ſubiectes quiet and orderly: but if affection will be above reaſon, if the childe maie checke the father, if the ſubiect maie overrule the Prince, if the feete ſhall direct the heade, what maie bee looked for but confuſion of head and feete? Our affections (if we take not heede of them) will cauſe vs to forget charity as <hi>Caine</hi> did,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</note> who beeing angry with <hi>Abell,</hi> gave place to his paſſion of anger, and followed his affection of hatred ſo farre, that he contemned Gods admonition. They will cauſe <hi>Eli</hi> to ſuffer his children and ſervauntes to ſinne vnpuniſhed;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.</note> and <hi>David</hi> to bewaile that proude traitour <hi>Abſolon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.</note> more then a whole army of good men. They will cauſe <hi>Ionas</hi> ſo to ſinne for the loſſe of a wilde gourde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jonas.</hi> 4.</note> as if either there were no more gourdes in the worlde, or no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing then the ſhaddowe of a wilde gourde. They wil cauſe <hi>Achab</hi> to come home to his houſe with heauy cheere,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</note> becauſe he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not get <hi>Nabaoths</hi> vinyard. What is contrary to the regiment of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Affection: what hindereth all equity &amp; iuſtice? Affection: what nouriſheth ſtrife and contentions? Affection. If affection ſo blinded <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that hee
<pb facs="tcp:20327:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
could not ſee to deale iuſtly with his ſonne <hi>Iacob;</hi> then muſt Iudges and Magiſtrates beware of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: for it blindeth not fooles but wiſemen, not wicked, but good men, not young, but olde men. The Lord hath made Magiſtrats his Miniſters of iuſtice, for the welfare of his people: they are to ſee to it, that of a fonde affection they beare not to much with <hi>Eſau,</hi> but that they helpe poore <hi>Iacob</hi> to his right. They ſhould have ſtill in their minde <hi>Iehoſaphats</hi> ſaying to the Magiſtrats,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 9. <hi>verſe.</hi> 6.</note> whom he appointed over the people: take heede what you doe, for yee execute not the iudgement, of man, but of the Lorde: and hee will bee with you in the cauſe and iudgement. Wherefore now let the feare of the Lorde be vpon you: take heede and doe it, for there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor receiving of rewarde. If I ſhoulde ſpeake of your duties in ſmal aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and in your abſence (as ſome deale with the grave fathers of our Church) I might ſeeme to tell them your duties, but not their owne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if in this famous place I ſhoulde entreate only of the dueties of the multitude: then were I like the fooliſh Phiſition that ſtudieth medicines for the feete, but none for the heade: if yee bee diſtempered with affections, and have thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſeaſes, they are the more hurtfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are neere the heade: in you lyeth the wealth and woe of the Lande.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prover.</hi> 28.</note> As a roaring
<pb facs="tcp:20327:16"/>
               <hi>Lyon</hi> and a hungry <hi>Beare:</hi> ſo is a wicked ruler over the poore people: a good Magiſtrate is a ſhephearde, and a father; but an vngodly, is a <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and a <hi>Beare,</hi> yea a roaring <hi>Lyon,</hi> and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <hi>Beare.</hi> When <hi>David</hi> kept his fathers ſheepe, there came a <hi>Lyon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.</note> and a <hi>Beare,</hi> &amp; tooke a ſheepe out of the flocke: <hi>David</hi> had ſuch care of his ſheep, that he went after them, &amp; ſmote them, and tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his ſheepe out of the mouth of the <hi>Lyon.</hi> The poore people are the ſheepe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they are committed to your cuſtody, to defende them by law and iuſtice, from the iawes of all <hi>Lyons</hi> and <hi>Beares,</hi> I meane from all oppreſſors and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Nimrods.</hi> You ſhoulde adventure your lives for them, if yee bee good ſhepheardes: defende the poore, protect the weake, deliver the innocent, be as good to poore chriſtians co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to your protection, as <hi>David</hi> was to dumbe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which his father appointed him to watch over. It is a ſtrange <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> or change, that a carefull ſhephearde ſhould be turned into a roaring <hi>Lyon</hi> or hungry <hi>Beare,</hi> that will ſpare none. Blinde affection and rewardes, and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons will cauſe this chaunge, <hi>Vix re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet gladium firmiter, vncta manus;</hi> The hand that is annointed wil hardly hold the ſword in it. <hi>Quatuor illa, timor, munus, dilectio, rancor: ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ſolent rectos hominum pervertere ſenſus;</hi> theſe foure thinges, feare, rewarde, love, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
<pb facs="tcp:20327:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doe oftentimes pervert the right ſences of men. You knowe that to true iudgement theſe thinges are required: firſt that it proceede from the light of reaſon, and not from the heate of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: will a wiſe man anſwere as ſpeaking in the winde? and will hee fill his ſtomake with heat?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.</note> Secondly it muſt be done without any reſpect of perſons: iudge right whether to a ſtraunger,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.</note> &amp;c. 3. An vpright iudge muſt not yeeld to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cry of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, nor to the favour of any:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.</note> followe not the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude &amp;c. fourthly hee muſt enquire of the matter diligently: the cauſe that I knew not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.7.</note> I ſought out diligently. Fiftly no feare of man muſt cauſe him to forſake a iuſt cauſe. Sixtly he muſt not be to pittifull: <hi>non miſereberis pauperi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.</note> ſaith the Lorde. Seventhly hee muſt take no rewardes. Eightly they muſt indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly hear both parties: it is not the cuſtome of the <hi>Romanes &amp;c. Actes</hi> 25.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actes.</hi> 25.</note> If all your iudgementes doe proceede of the light of reaſon and not of any paſſion or affection of minde: if ye have ſtill a reſpect to the cauſe and not to the perſon: if yee liſten to the cry of iuſtice and not to mens ſuites: if you perfectly examine al matters: if your iudgements be neither hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by feare, nor perverted by rewards, nor defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by fooliſh compaſſion: then ſhal you be meanes to eſtabliſh the Princes throne: you ſhall bee mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of many bleſſings to this lande: and the ſides of the poore ſhall bleſſe you: but if ye iuſtifie
<pb facs="tcp:20327:17"/>
the wicked for a rewarde, and take away the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of the righteous from him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.</note> then ſurely as the flame of fire devoureth the ſtubble, and as the chaffe is conſumed of the flame; ſo your roote ſhall be as rottennes and your bud ſhall riſe vp as duſt: becauſe yee have caſt off the law of the Lorde of hoſtes, and contemned the word of the holy one of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> The king of <hi>Perſia</hi> being offended at <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus,</hi> gave the <hi>Athenians</hi> thirty thouſand pieces of the great coine of golde, wherein was ingraven an archer of golde; which thing when <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> vnderſtoode, he ſaide merrily, but yet truly, that he was driven away with thirty thouſande archers. Many a poore <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> in this land is (I feare) oftentimes put from his right by a great company of Angels that come againſt him: our Engliſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are as ſtrong as the <hi>Perſian</hi> archers: but it is pitty that either archers there, or Angels heere, ſhould fight againſt iuſtice and right. If hee were not able to reſiſt thirty thouſand archers, howe ſhoulde poore men ſtande againſt an army of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, when they march againſt them? Surelie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Godly and famous Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates doe quit themſelves like men: nay vnleſſe they ſhew themſelves to be Gods: the Angels will firſt overcome them, and then ſoone overthrow the poore. When the Lord woulde threaten the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> a moſt grievous plague, hee ſaith in the 11. of <hi>Zachary,</hi> that hee will raiſe vp a ſhephearde in the
<pb facs="tcp:20327:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that ſhal not looke for the thing that is loſt, nor ſeeke the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der lambes, nor heale that that is hurt, nor feed that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtandeth vp: but he ſhal eat the fleſh of the fat, &amp; teare their clawes in pieces. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtandeth in the aſſembly of Gods: he iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among Gods. Howe long will yee iudge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, and accept the perſons of men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. I hope it cannot be truely ſaide of you, as it was of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>In medio veſtrum eſt que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vos neſcitis.</hi> My minde is not to accuſe any one, but to admoniſh every one:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.</note> (if yong <hi>Samuel</hi> may adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe olde <hi>Eli</hi>) wiſhing them to bee as farre from the ſinnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> as they wiſh his puniſhment to bee farre remooved from them. Let <hi>Phinees</hi> and <hi>Hophnes</hi> though gentlemen offenders, yea though <hi>Elies</hi> kinſmen, yea though they bee <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> ſonnes, if they meddle with the workes of darkeneſſe, let them have the wages of ſinne which is death, for the ſervice they haue done to <hi>Satan.</hi> You knowe that <hi>Proſopolepſia,</hi> is forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.</note> Looke not on the face of the perſon, but beholde well the cauſe. The poore man flieth in his trouble to the Magiſtrate for ſuccour, as vnto a ſhaddowe againſt the heate: a refuge againſt the tempeſt: if the magiſtrate bee vnrighteous and ledde by affection and not by iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the confidence that is put in him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.</note> is like a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oth, and a ſliding foote, the more ye truſt them, the more are ye deceived. <hi>Chryſippus</hi> being
<pb facs="tcp:20327:18"/>
demaunded why he did not take charge of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth vpon him, anſwered that the reaſon was, foraſmuch as if he governed ill, hee muſt needes diſpleaſe God, if well, he muſt needes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe men: but as he was afraide to diſpleaſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God or man, ſo the vnrighteous iudge will not feare to diſpleaſe both God and man. When <hi>Ioſia</hi> iudged the cauſe of the poore &amp; afflicted, did not he proſper? and was not this becauſe he knewe me, ſaith the Lord? <hi>Iob</hi> delivered the poore &amp; helpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, and did not the Lord hedge him and his houſe rounde about? Our gratious dreade ſoveraigne, (whom God make a moſt aged mother in <hi>Iſrael</hi>) dealeth moſt graciouſly with poore ſubiectes, liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning moſt carefully, and ſpeaking moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vnto them, and commaunding that iuſtice bee done accordingly. If it be no diſgrace to her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nay a ſpeciall honour to deliver the oppreſſed: it can be no blot to inferiour Magiſtrates. If the Princes throne be eſtabliſhed by iuſtice: then doth it concerne the ſafety of Magiſtrates to doe iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: otherwiſe the ſtone ſhall cry out of the wal, and the beame out of the timber ſhall aunſwere: they ſhal give in their evidence like honeſt iurates againſt the houſes of all oppreſſours. It will bee time for men to heare when the ſtone ſhall cry out of the wal, I am built by iniquity, by vſury, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion; and the beame out of the timber ſhal aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, I am built with bloud &amp; oppreſſion. There
<pb facs="tcp:20327:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are many ſuch houſes built in theſe evil daies: but the builders have conſulted ſhame to their owne houſes, &amp; have ſinned againſt their owne ſoules, as ſpeaketh <hi>Abacuk</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abac.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Ioachim</hi> a rich op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour may cloſe himſelf in <hi>Cedar;</hi> but the Lord will plucke him away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thornes, &amp; his poſteritie with fiſhookes. But in the meane time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 4. <hi>verſe.</hi> 2.</note> where the hedge is lowe, every man goeth over: the hedge is low with the widdow, ſhe hath no husband; with the orphane, hee hath no father; with the ſtranger, he hath no friend; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, he hath no wealth: the plougher, I meane, the oppreſſour plougheth on their backes, and maketh long furrowes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 29</note> they have none to defende them, but the iudge, who ſhould be a father, and the Lawier a patron. The Iudges in <hi>Aegypt</hi> were bound by oth to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt iuſtice, no not at the kings comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: &amp; they ware about their neckes a chaine of golde, with the image of truth in it. The Lorde hath made you (ye learned Lawiers) patrons of the poore, &amp; ye cal them clients: take heed that ye bereave not poore <hi>Iacob</hi> of his right. I am of <hi>Thales</hi> minde, that that common-wealth is moſt happy &amp; ſafe, where men give leaſt heede to Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers, &amp; moſt heed to the law it ſelfe. There are two thinges required in euery Lawier: the firſt is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſkill; the ſeconde is a tender conſcience. If yee be not ſeaſoned with both, yee are vnſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. A tender conſcience without learning and ſkil,
<pb facs="tcp:20327:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is vnfruitfull, but learning and skill without conſcience is diveliſh: &amp; an vnconſcionable Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ier is more to be feared, then an vnſkilfull: and yet the vnskilfull Lawier receiving the rewarde, but not doing the duty of a good Lawier, committeth theft. The Lorde hath beutified in any of you, with verie manie, and very excellent giftes. Now are you to labour that it maie bee ſaide of you, as our Saviour ſaide of <hi>Nathaniell;</hi> beholde, a true <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite</hi> without guile beholde a true Lawier void of corruption. The Lorde hath made all patrons of benefices his inſtrumentes for <hi>Iacobs</hi> behoofe: but they beſtow (for the moſt part) <hi>Iacobs</hi> living on profane <hi>Eſau.</hi> Alas that ever the clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould draw &amp; drinke in even into her very bowels, the deadly poiſon of covetouſnes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and nowe a daies ſimony is an open and an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie way to have a living: the maide ſimony, that kept the doore in popery, is crept into patrons houſes, and ſuffereth not <hi>Peter</hi> only to come in, but every meane fellow is admitted, ſometimes of favour, at <hi>Iohns</hi> requeſt: but commonly the Church doore is opened with a ſilver key: and manie a lewde patron, by his marte and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of mens ſoules, maketh a living: whereby wee ſee it is come to paſſe, that manie doe denie <hi>Chriſt</hi> in their deedes, and the love to mens ſoules waxeth colde, while they warme themſelves at the fire of riches, which is kindled
<pb facs="tcp:20327:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and blowne with the bellowes of covetouſneſſe, and yet with no crowing of cockes, or prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of conſcience, canne thoſe covetous patrons bee awaked, albeit the LORDE doe merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie looke vppon them, and in their owne heartes doe condemne their impiety: but grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing olde and obſtinate, in the drouſie diſeaſe and abominable dropſie of covetouſneſſe, they drawe ſinne vnto them with cordes of vanitie and iniquity, as it were with cart-ropes. It is ſaide by the Prophet, that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhal ſucke the milke of the gentiles: but manie of our gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles ſucke the milke, naie the bloude out of the Churches breſtes. It was woont to bee ſaide of Friers, that they were fedde fatte with mens ſinnes: a man may ſay the ſame of manie patrons falſelie ſo called. It was merrilie and truely ſaide of one, that the ſtate of Aſſes, was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſtate of Horſes: for the Horſes runne to patrons for benefices: but many ignoraunt Aſſes doe obtaine them. Have they no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſaith the Lorde, that they eat vp my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as if they would eat bread? they have not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon God. Have theſe cruel patrons no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that they eate vp Gods meſſengers as if they would eate bread? they have not called vpon God. Wel, I ſay no more but this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> O thou vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous patron, thou abhorreſt idols, &amp; committeſt thou ſacriledge? The name of God is blaſphemed
<pb facs="tcp:20327:20"/>
among the papiſtes through you. The Lord hath made the phiſitions of mens bodies, his miniſters of health: they ſhoulde deale with poore <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> as well as with rich <hi>Eſau.</hi> The Lord hath made fathers &amp; maſters, miniſters of many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to their children and ſervantes: they ſhoulde defraude them of the graces of God in no caſe. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally every one of vs faithfull ſtewards, and good diſpoſers of the manifold graces of God, ſhoulde employ them to the honour of God, and benefit of our brethren. Let vs remembring <hi>Iſaac his</hi> frailty and fal, ſhake off all ſecurity of the fleſh, and be the more fervent in praier and watchful in weldoing, that we be not overcome of our affections. Thus the ſecure are taught to awake, and watch, and the holy are warned not to preſume of their ſtrength, ſeeing <hi>Iſaac</hi> hath fallen. The afflicted that are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with the ſight of their ſins, have this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple written for the comfort of their conſciences. O thou afflicted and toſſed with tempeſt, that haſt no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.</note> behold &amp;c. This is vnto me as the water of <hi>Noah &amp;c.</hi> Finally we learne, that the examples of the beſt men are not at al times, and in al thinges to be followed: &amp; that there is no man ſo perfect, but that another may ſay vnto him, phiſition cure thy ſelfe. Thus having ſeene the frailty of <hi>Iſaac</hi> in that he was led by a blind affection, let vs ſee in few words, into the pollicy of <hi>Rebecca:</hi> who by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct means got <hi>Iacob</hi> the bleſſing. As there was
<pb facs="tcp:20327:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a general principle of faith in <hi>Iſaac his</hi> mind, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bleſſing his ſonne, ſealed the aſſurance of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, and the right of the inheritance vnto him, ſo was there in <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> minde, when by her ſubtile practiſe ſhee procured the bleſſing to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> Albeit ſhee coulde not rule her husbande by wholſome counſell; yet this was not the beſt waie to circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vent him with ſuch a deceit why doth ſhee not patiently expect and wait, till God performe his promis vnto <hi>Iacob?</hi> ſhe knewe his decree was immutable, his promiſe infallible, and therefore ſhee doth ill to obſcure the heavenly oracle with a lie: but ſee the earneſtnes of her faith accompanied with an vndiſcreet zeale; ſhee adventureth to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke her husband againſt her, to make mortal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred betweene the brethren, and to bring her ſonne <hi>Iacob</hi> into preſent daunger. Behold what a raſh, and inconſiderate zeale will doe. Here we ſee that pure and ſound knowledge doth not alwaies ſhine in the mindes of the godly, but the ſmall light that ſheweth them the way is obſcured, and darkened with many clouds of ignoraunce, and miſtes of affection. The Lord beſtoweth on man the gift of perfection, knowledge, &amp; truth, as it were a beame of the ſunne into a houſe of clay, to give vs light &amp; warmth: howbeit this beam (though the more the ſonne of righteouſnes aſcendeth &amp; commeth daily neare vnto vs, the greater light &amp; warmth it yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) yet it doth not overſhine vs all with ful light
<pb facs="tcp:20327:21"/>
of truth and heate of holineſſe, as long as wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in theſe houſes of clay. A Chriſtian man or woman hath the beames of the ſunne, but as in a houſe, not in the open heaven: ſometimes it is ſhaddowed and made dimme with darkeneſſe, ſometimes it wareth faint through colde. To bee ſhort a generall faith hath the preeminence in the Godly, as in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> ſo that they either ſwarve out of the way, or ſtumble in the way: but whereas Gods election ſtoode ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe firme: nay whereas hee executeth his counſell, and effecteth his purpoſe by the ſubtelty of a woman: by this meanes hee procureth to his goodnes the whole praiſe of the bleſſing. In the dimnes of <hi>Iſaac his</hi> ſight, there are two examples of Gods providence; the one generall, the other ſpecial. General, in that olde men are deprived of their ſight before they dye: that by howe much leſſe they knowe theſe outwarde thinges, they may have the more knowledge of inwarde, and heavenly matters. And ſo in the very defect of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the worke of Gods providence appeareth. Speciall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prove.</hi> 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</note> in that by the occaſion of the dimnes of his ſight, the bleſſing was conferred on <hi>Iacob: I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> ſhall looſe his eie ſight, but <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhall have his right in the bleſſing. This good father maketh his choice of his meates, after the delight of his caſt: and this may the godly doe with thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to the God, who hath not made the honie-combe
<pb facs="tcp:20327:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for Drone-bees. But yet eaſe and fatneſſe ſtaieth the flooliſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.</note> and the proſperity of fooles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroieth them. Wo bee to them that are at eaſe in <hi>Sion &amp;c.</hi> They are glad of their own eaſe: but not ſorry for their brothers diſeaſe: they are glad for their owne proſperity: they are not ſorry for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> adverſity: they are glad of their owne dainty fare, but they are not ſorry for the penury of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chea,</hi> who is fedde with the bred of teares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.</note> &amp; with the waters of affliction: they are glad of their own glory, theſe weigh not the contempt and ſlaunder of <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> but as ſome doe ſacrifice the fatteſt to God belly, without either feare of <hi>Iehova,</hi> or care of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſo ſome having got much by vnlawfull means, have no power to ſpend it vpon themſelves as <hi>Salomon</hi> witneſſeth, that the deceitfull man roſteth, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he took in hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting. And without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture even olde <hi>Iſaac</hi> permitted <hi>Eſau</hi> to hunt to much &amp; to far, chiefely to ſatiſfie his curious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit. The Saintes of God are not Angels: but if they labour not to live Godly, they are not Saintes. See the providence of GOD for <hi>Iacob,</hi> that <hi>Iſaac</hi> doeth not immediatly bleſſe <hi>Eſau:</hi> but ſendeth him for veniſon, promiſing him the bleſſing at his returne: but God diſpoſeth it according to his good pleaſure. <hi>Iacob</hi> is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly turned into <hi>Eſau:</hi> ſmoth <hi>Iacob</hi> into rough <hi>Eſau:</hi> but in out daies the rough <hi>Eſaus</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world,
<pb facs="tcp:20327:22"/>
the mighty hunters, the prophane <hi>Machiaveliſts,</hi> are turnd outwardly into <hi>Iacob:</hi> but al is for ſome outward bleſſing: for <hi>Iacob,</hi> wil be <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtil, and <hi>Eſau,</hi> wil be <hi>Eſau.</hi> It was culpable, and blame-worthy in <hi>Rebecca,</hi> to faſhion <hi>Iacob</hi> otherwiſe then hee was by nature: yea, to doe it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her husband, and to cauſe <hi>Eſaus</hi> garmentes to be worne to his owne loſſe. If theſe meanes of fraud, lying, and fatning, be not agoed cauſe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right agreeing with the counſell and will of God: who can excuſe the wicked in theſe daies who in vnlawful matters, vſe vnlawful meanes? as in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering their childrens, if not their ſonnes, yet their daughters faces &amp; favours, by painting and other vanities; yea in making them to put on ſtraunge &amp; mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous attire, meeter for <hi>Giantes,</hi> then gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weomen: in deceiving they paſſe not who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: in vſing a mans own knife, to cut his own throate. I may cry out with <hi>Michea:</hi> truſt not in a friend &amp;c. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> noteth two miſteries in this hiſtory; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one is that vnder the goates ſkinnes, and apparell of <hi>Eſau,</hi> holy <hi>Iacob</hi> was bleſt: ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnder the ſhape of a ſinful man, deſerved the bleſſing, beeing made ſinne for vs. The ſecond miſtery is this, that albeit the miniſter of Gods word &amp; Sacraments, be the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God whilſt he miniſtreth theſe thinges: yet hee cannot apply Gods graces after his owne will, but after the will and purpoſe of God. But we may moſt fitly allud to this hiſtorie
<pb facs="tcp:20327:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in that we know that no man canne be allowed or bleſſed of God, but in an other mans name &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, even in the perſon of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> We muſt all put on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if wee will have any bleſſing at Gods hands. If all this were done by <hi>Rebecca</hi> &amp; <hi>Iacob</hi> at Gods appointment, it was no ſinne but a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. To kill a mans ſonne without Gods expreſſe commandement, to rob a mans neighbour, to put an offender to death, beeing no Magiſtrate, are grievous ſins: yet <hi>Abraham</hi> is highly prayſed of God for his readines to doe the firſt, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for the ſecond, <hi>Phinees</hi> for the laſt. That this was done by Gods ordinaunce, ſome learned men doe bring ſomewhat probable and likely, but not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrative reaſons: as firſt the oracle of God ſhewing <hi>Rebecca</hi> that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhoulde bee bleſt, may ſeeme to prove this to be of God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that <hi>Rebecca</hi> was preſent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſpake to <hi>Eſau,</hi> argueth Gods providence. Thirdly <hi>Iſaac</hi> his blindnes doeth concur to further <hi>Iacob.</hi> Fourthly he perceiveth the voice to be <hi>Iacobs,</hi> &amp; yet is deceived and bleſſeth him. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ftly he diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not betweene kids fleſh and veniſon, being v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to veniſon: ſo that it ſeemeth the Lord tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the iudgement of another ſence, for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake. Sixtly ſeeing himſelfe to be deceived, he doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine of <hi>Iacob,</hi> much leſſe revoke the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, nay he confirmeth it to <hi>Iacob.</hi> Finally there is a ſpace given to <hi>Iacob</hi> to departe with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing:
<pb facs="tcp:20327:23"/>
and immediatly <hi>Eſau</hi> commeth in. Becauſe of theſe reaſons, I ſay if <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Rebecca</hi> did this without Gods appointment, it was <hi>bonum,</hi> but not <hi>benè,</hi> the matter was good, the manner nought: but if it were doone by GODS com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, which I dare not denie but it might bee, (but I will not affirme that it was, becauſe Gods worde doeth not affirme) but if the manner was of God, it was blameleſſe altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but howſoever it was, I ſay, and you ſee with <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> that the counſell of GOD cannot bee hindered. Have not the bleſſings of <hi>Englande,</hi> diverſe and ſundrye wayes by the bloudie <hi>Guizes,</hi> and <hi>Italian Gog,</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Magog,</hi> beene miſchievouſlie aſſailed from time to time? But prayſed, and prayſed for ever, bee that GOD that helpeth vs, and powreth dailie his benefites vppon vs; hee hath overthrowen the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> attempt, and the <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> practiſe: hee hath prepared him deadly wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, hee hath whette his ſwoorde, hee hath bent his bowe, hee hath ordained his arrowes againſt the face of theſe perſecutours: ſo that they are falne into the pitte that they made for vs. The miſchiefe is returned on their owne heade, and their crueltie is falne on their owne pate. Put them ſtill thus in feare O LORDE, that they may knowe themſelves to bee but men. And in aſmuch as the counſels of GOD cannot bee
<pb facs="tcp:20327:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hindered by any pollicie or power of man, I wiſh with all my hearte, that our learned and grave Fathers woulde ſomewhat refraine themſelves from them that ſue for reformation, and let them alone; for if this counſell or this worke be of men. it will come to nought; but if it bee of God they cannot deſtroy it, leſt they be founde even fighters againſt God. And withall the veines of my ſoule I wiſh, that they that ſeeke reformation, would take heede, that they make not the cauſe the worſe, by their vndiſcreete zeale, vnbrotherlie reproches, vnchriſtian ſlaunders, vnſaverie and vnlearned libels, and almoſt Phariſaicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte of their fathers and brethren. For my owne parte, GOD is my witneſſe, whome I ſerve in my ſpirite, in the goſpell of his ſonne, that without ceaſing I praye for the peace of the Church, and for a learned miniſterie. You knowe that diſcorde in the Church is fire in a houſe: and a continuall fever in the bodie. The LORDE quench this fire, and cure this fever. Wee prayed for outwarde peace, when our enemies were at hande: and nowe GOD hath ſente it, doe wee nouriſh conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions inwardely and at home among our ſelves? Inwarde diſſention, or contention, is a gappe not onelye for the bloud-thirſtie Papiſt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who hath no other deſire then our deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:20327:24"/>
do other ſcope then our ſpoile: but no other meanes, but our contentions: but it is a gappe to let in <hi>Satan,</hi> he entreth at our vnchriſtian brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. But to ſpeake ſomewhat more of <hi>Iacob</hi> and ſo to ende; we ſee he ſtealeth his bleſſing, but wee have many that ſteale the bleſſings which at none of theirs. I cite them all to ſtande at the tribunal ſeat of the eternall iudge. I leave the poore known theeves to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon barres; and here I firſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon thoſe ſacrilegious perſons, that feare not to ſteale holy thinges, that make a mocke of that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Sacriledge will be ſinne one day. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying of publike things to privat vſes, wil prove theft one day. Te comming in by Simony wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be theft. Yea the ſtealing of the heartes of the people from the paſtors, will be prooved theft. And you famous Merchantes &amp; other occupiers in this citty, take heed that theft like birdlime cleave not faſt to ſome of your fingers. And you that are tutors of widdowes and Orphans goods, beware that ye be not appeached of theft. You that are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, take heede that ye come not in the number. The cauſes of theft, at firſt the perverſnes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s heart, ſecondly incredulity, thirdly vnfaithfulnes, fourthly covetouſnes, fiftly eaſe and idlenes, ſixtly ſurfetting, ſeventhly occaſion: I ſcarce make po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty one cauſe, for ſuch theeves are almoſt as worthy of pitty, as of puniſhment. A man may bee guilty of theft, by dealing in it, by concealing of it,
<pb facs="tcp:20327:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by counſelling to it, by commaunding or commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it. <hi>Iacob</hi> was timorous in ſtealing his owne, theſe are impudent in taking other mens: <hi>Iacob</hi> was even forced to theſe meanes, they runne to al wicked meanes: <hi>Iacob</hi> did it but once, it is their daily practiſe: <hi>Iacob</hi> would ſoone have beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, but even Gods word ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not diſſwade theſe men from ſpoiling and robbing the Church, the fatherles, and ſtranger. I had left out the Abbey-lubbers in our Church, who are mighty theeves. Though the Abbeies be gone, yet they remaine. I meane ſuch as will not worke: whether it be ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill or ſpirituall worke, it is plaine theeverie to take the daies wages, and not to do a daies worke for it. The Lord our God enlighten our mindes, and ſanctifie our heartes with ſuch a portion of his ſpirit, and with that meaſure of his grace, that we may be fully perſwaded, that this worldes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is full of anguiſh, the ſecurity of the worlde without foundation, the feare of the worlde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out comforte, the travels of the worlde without fruit, the ſorrow of the worlde without profitte, the deſires of the worlde without ſucceſſe, the hope of the worlde without rewarde, and the mirth of the worlde without continuance, and the miſeries of the worlde without remedies, and that all the worlde is but vanity of vanities. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that our heartes may bee inwardlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and thoroughlie certified, that the lawe
<pb facs="tcp:20327:25"/>
of the Lorde is an vndefiled lawe, conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſoule &amp;c. <hi>The God of peace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20327:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
